<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short, but a strict account taken of Babylons merchants vvho are now forcing the sale of their old, rusty, cankered ware upon the people of these nations : and a stretching them out by their line (which as they say) is the Scriptures in the New Testament, ad they call themselves Christian ministers : also a comparing them with those that spake them forth as their examples that all people may see with whom they run paralel [sic] / by one that hath fed upon the whores flesh these many years handed to him by these merchants and their brethren, but now witnesseth it in him consumed by fire, Richard Crane.</title>
            <author>R. C. (Richard Crane)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11062622</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11062622</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46207</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46207)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1421:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short, but a strict account taken of Babylons merchants vvho are now forcing the sale of their old, rusty, cankered ware upon the people of these nations : and a stretching them out by their line (which as they say) is the Scriptures in the New Testament, ad they call themselves Christian ministers : also a comparing them with those that spake them forth as their examples that all people may see with whom they run paralel [sic] / by one that hath fed upon the whores flesh these many years handed to him by these merchants and their brethren, but now witnesseth it in him consumed by fire, Richard Crane.</title>
                  <author>R. C. (Richard Crane)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46207:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46207:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A ſhort, But a Strict Account Taken of BABYLONS MERCHANTS VVho are now Forcing the Sale of their Old, Ruſty, Cankered Ware, upon the People of theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>And a ſtretching them out by their Line, (which as they ſay) is the Scriptures in the New Teſtament, as they call Themſelves Chriſtian Miniſters; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a comparing them with thoſe that ſpake them forth as their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that all People may ſee with whom they run Paralel.</p>
            <p>By one that hath fed upon the Whores Fleſh theſe many Years, Handed to him by theſe Merchants, and their Brethren; But now Witneſſeth it in him Conſumed by Fire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>RICHARD CRANE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the Signe of the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth,</hi> near Alderſgate, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46207:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46207:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHoever Thou art, or to whoſe hands this may come to be Read, be not haſty to Judge, or Cenſure, before thou haſt, with that which is juſt of God in thy Conſcience, weighed the thing, and then with that, moderately Judge, and Honeſtly in the ſight of God, ſearch the Scriptures, which maketh mention of a Chriſtian Miniſtry and Miniſters, and ſee if amongſt them all a Paralel be found of our Miniſtrie of <hi>England,</hi> in this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, (who calls themſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel, and of Chriſt Jeſus,) either in Call, Doctrine, Practice, Maintenance, Life, or Converſation; and if by true ſearch, and by meaſuring and compare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, they be found neither to anſwer Rule, nor Example, ſpoken of in the Scriptures of Truth, where mention is made of Chriſtian Miniſters, thou wilt and muſt with me conclude, that they are to be denyed; for ſuch as is found in the <hi>Words,</hi> and not in the <hi>Life,</hi> are falſe, Being compared with them who in the Life ſpake the words that they now Read and Preach out of the Life, which is Abomination and a Lie; For the Scriptures that were ſpoken forth by the Apoſtles, and Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus, through the motion of the <hi>Eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> were not left upon Record for that end, for to be a Foundation to build Inventions, and Imaginations there upon; And ſo declare and Preach People into the Words, but not into the Life of the Words, which the Miniſters of Chriſt did; For they ſaid, <hi>be ye follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of us, as we are of Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> So here the Life and Words were not ſeperated, but went together; now the Life and Words are divided, and ſo the <hi>form of Godlineſſe,</hi> but <hi>not the Power,</hi> is held forth; And ſuch as are Miniſters of the Form, we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to turn from, and not own in the leaſt; Now if they be found Paralel with Antichriſtian Miniſters which were ſuch as had the form, but denyed the Life, let them be eſteemed even ſuch as they are, for that is a thing juſt and equal, to ſay or ſpeak of men even as
<pb facs="tcp:46207:3"/>
they are, and no otherwiſe, being <hi>the Tree is known by his Fruits;</hi> I have not the leaſt hatred or prejudice upon me, to theſe mens perſons who calls themſelves Chriſtian Miniſters, the Lord God bears me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; but to that which works the wonders of deceit and lyes, in the Creature, I have abſolute enmity with, and it is that which in the fear of the Lord God I teſtifie, <hi>with my Life, Soul, and Spirit,</hi> againſt, and my whole ſtrength; that the Creature may know to witneſſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from the Bondage, with which it is Captivated, and may come to be ſet free; which cannot be done, till the mind come to be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a meaſure of Gods Spirit, manifeſt in the Creature; by which thou wilt ſee, and know what is thy duty in ſhort, both to God and man, as he hath (unto thee) made it known; that is to do juſtly, love Mercy, walk Humbly with thy God, <hi>Mic. 6.8,</hi> And profeſſe what thou wilt, I tell thee, except thou comes to have thy mind turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which is his manifeſtation in thee, thy profeſsion will not hid nor cover thee, from the day that is coming upon all Hypocrites, both Teachers and Hearers, and all Drunkards, Swearers, Whore-mongers, Lyars, and all profane Perſons whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which is for the Lake of Gods fearful vengence, except true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance be witneſſed, and the evil turned from.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:46207:3"/>
            <p>GO to now ye Merchants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who are now in this day bringing forth and expoſing to Sale, your old Cankered, Ruſty and moth-eaten ware, unto the People of this Nation of <hi>England;</hi> for in the <hi>Light</hi> of the Lord God I have beheld you, which maketh both you and your confuſed ware manifeſt; Rage not, neither be you angry if you be brought to your <hi>Rule,</hi> which you ſay is the Scripture, and to your examples which are they that ſpake them forth, and you thereby meaſured and compared, Firſt you call your ſelves <hi>Chriſtian Miniſters</hi> (if ſo) we will ſee whether you run paralel with the Chriſtian Miniſters in the Scriptures of Truth mentioned, if you do; then you are to be owned, if not, then to be denyed; The Diſciples who were followers of Jeſus was ſent forth into his Miniſtry; and his comand was, <hi>Provide neither Gold, nor Silver, nor Braſs in your purſes, nor Scrip for your journey, neither two Coats, neither ſhoos, nor yet ſtaves; for the work-man is worthy of his meat; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Citie they did enter, they were to enquire who in it was worthy, and there abide till they went thence,</hi> and they did ſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. And they were <hi>freely to give</hi> as they had received; and when they returned they were asked <hi>if they lacked any thing,</hi> and they ſaid nay; now what is your Rule for your indenting with peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in a Pariſh, and ſaying I will be your Miniſter, provided <hi>you will give me ſo much a year,</hi> and if they will not give it you, you will be none of their Miniſter, but looks out for a better Market; Is your Rule for this in Scripture, and where is your example for ſo doing? do you anſwer your examples? (the Diſciples of Jeſus) you dare not ſay you do; then why are you to be owned Chriſtian Miniſters, anſwering neither Rule nor example in Scripture; neither are you Goſpel Miniſters; for the Goſpel of Chriſt is <hi>the Power of God,</hi> and the Power of God you never knew, neither witneſſed; and the Goſpel of Jeſus owns no ſuch Miniſters as you, neither doth the true Church of whom <hi>Chriſt is Head,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Faith</hi> he is <hi>defender of,</hi> know any ſuch as you are to Miniſter unto them; and where is your Rule in Scripture for the compelling your falſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46207:4"/>
maintenance by <hi>Tythes, and ſueing men at Law,</hi> and not only ſo, but caſting into Priſon and taking treble damage; did ever the Miniſters of Chriſt do ſo? Read the Scripture and ſee Chriſts Comand was, <hi>Sue no man at the Law;</hi> and theſe pretended Chriſtian Minſters, they take no notice of that, as though his comands were not to be obſerved in this genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; you take not them the Apoſtles ſpeaks of for your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples; <hi>that wandered up &amp; down in ſheep-skins and Goat-skins, &amp; lye in dens and Caves of the Earth, and had no certain dwelling place, of whom the World was not worthy;</hi> But your condition is far otherwiſe, for you have certain dwelling places, if not the beſt in a Pariſh, the ſecond beſt; and ſo the world that lyeth in wickedneſs is worthy of you, and you Miniſter unto them; I have even ſtood amazed when I have beheld you, as you are every way in deceit in your Functions, or trades, your calls unto it, your names, your geſtures, and actions, your lives and converſations, and all falſe and a lye; becauſe you call your ſelves <hi>Chriſtian Miniſters</hi> and are not, But Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians; for in nothing you paralel the true Miniſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but in many things the falſe, as I ſhall make it appear, for the ſake of the Ignorant, amongſt whom is your chief ſeat; the Scriptures maketh mention of two ſorts of Miniſters (that is to ſay) <hi>of Chriſt and of Antichriſt;</hi> Miniſters of Chriſt you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay you are, becauſe you examplifie not Chriſts Miniſters mentioned in Scriptures; if you were, your <hi>Fruits</hi> would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, for by your <hi>Fruits</hi> you are known; and ſo in the Light of Chriſt your cheat is ſeen; for truly never did <hi>I</hi> hear or read of amongſt all the Trades-men and merchandizing Artiſts in the world, ſo groſs and ſordid a cheat, as Preaching in your way; the general Term of preaching amongſt you is called (Soul cure.)</p>
            <p>I have often asked of ſeveral of the Bretheren of your function, to ſatisfie me <hi>what the Soul is,</hi> that the great out-cry is made about, which is by your medicine to be cured; and I never could be ſatisfied, neither anſwered; but ſome would ſay one thing ſome another; One ſaid <hi>it could not be defined be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi> it <hi>comprehended the Body with all its faculties; and the Leſſer never comprehended the Greater, but the greater the leſs;</hi> and ſo being ignorant of the ſoul or what it is, your cure is you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46207:4"/>
know not what, or to what, and ſo truly Phyſitians worth nothing; where is your paralel in Scripture of this? Search the Scriptures, the Miniſters of Chriſt ſpake <hi>what they knew,</hi> and teſtified <hi>what they had ſeen,</hi> and what they had <hi>taſted, felt, and handled,</hi> even the <hi>Good Word of Life,</hi> that they Miniſtred unto the true Church; and they were edified, confirmed and ſtrengthened by it, and in it; That which is imortal was known, and ſo they knew what their Miniſtry was too; And ſuch Miniſters I own, Love, and can receive, and have uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with; for ſuch in this day are not to you known, but as enemies, and ſo you deal with them, and perſecute and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon them; If there was nothing elſe to make you mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, it would make you <hi>Antichriſts Miniſters;</hi> for the Miniſters of Chriſt never perſecuted, nor impriſoned any for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake; ſearch the Scriptures, and if you find that ever the Miniſters did ſo, call me lyar; and if you cannot, rail not upon me if I call you deceivers, and Antichriſt, for you are ſo aſſuredly.</p>
            <p>I have ſomething to ſay to your Medicine, which you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to cure Souls with; I would ask whether it be <hi>a Simple, or a Compound?</hi> You will hardly ſay it is a <hi>Simple,</hi> becauſe it is made as of ſo many <hi>Fragments,</hi> and of divers ſorts, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>Compound;</hi> I ſhall ſpeak ſomething to ſome of your <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients</hi> you uſe in the Compoſition ſo much cryed up; firſt you have <hi>Prayer,</hi> called <hi>Common,</hi> and indeed ſo it is, I hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know any thing more Common, except <hi>Curſing, and Swearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have <hi>Muſick,</hi> called <hi>Organ,</hi> with <hi>Surplice, Tippit, Hood, Scarfe, Girdle,</hi> and a hideous noiſe of ſinging (which the Lord God will turn into howling) with <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Boyes,</hi> train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in that exerciſe; and there is a thing called an <hi>Altar,</hi> with <hi>Railes</hi> to fence it in, and there is <hi>bowing,</hi> and <hi>cringing</hi> to a many <hi>turned Pillars;</hi> then there is a getting up into a thing called a <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and there is a Prayer as an <hi>Exordium</hi> to the Preachers Oration, then a verſe, or part of a verſe out of Scripture is taken, to be his <hi>Theam,</hi> or <hi>Text;</hi> and then he raiſes Doctrines, conſequences, uſes, and applications, and ſo rakes many <hi>Old Authors, as Jerom, Ambros, Auguſtine, Baſil, Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Luther,</hi> with many ſeveral others not here menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46207:5"/>
and ſo an hour or there abouts, puts an end to that <hi>Market,</hi> where this <hi>Medicine</hi> for <hi>ſoul-cure</hi> is ſold, and the ſale of it is much more abominable and a greater cheat, then the thing it ſelf, if poſſible; For in the firſt place, they ſell it at an exceeding dear rate, and when they have ſold it, they have it again, and doth ſo, may be ten or twenty times over, and many times more; and when the poor people comes to conſider what they have had for their money, and comes to examine it with the <hi>Light of Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> then they ſee they have had nothing but <hi>a Lye</hi> all along; and if I ſhould know any Trads-man either <hi>Manual,</hi> or <hi>Artiſt,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſhould ſo deal, as to ſell his Commodities, and have it again, once, much more ſo many times over, truly I ſhould poſt him up for a <hi>Cheat,</hi> and a <hi>Jugler,</hi> and ever renounce ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving dealings with him more; now you out-ſtrip all <hi>Tradſmen,</hi> or <hi>Artiſts</hi> whatever, in ſelling your <hi>Medicine,</hi> (called <hi>ſoul-cure</hi>) for if any that are convinced of the deceit of your ware, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to buy of you, you have a Law to compel them to buy; if they will not buy, nevertheleſſe you will have their money, which is a thing not practiced in any publick Market or Shop in <hi>England,</hi> or in the World (I may ſay) except in your own; for if men come into a publick Market, or Shop, the ſales-man of what Trade ſoever, doth not compel any to buy their ware, but leaves all to their freedom for their money; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they ſue men at Law, and caſt into Priſon, and when they have their bodies there, they do not <hi>plunder</hi> and ſpoyl their Goods, as you do; Now if it were lawful for any Trads-men ſo to do, I ſhould think, it ſhould (rather) be lawful for ſuch as ſold ſomething for their money; for what you ſell, is neither <hi>Meat, Drink, nor Cloth,</hi> but a <hi>Jugle,</hi> and a <hi>Lye;</hi> for not only I, but many thouſands in this Nation, hath left dealing in your Moth-eaten ware; Rage not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo called, for it is ſo, <hi>The Light of Chriſt Jeſus hath manifeſted it,</hi> And this I ſpeak to your torment, that Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and ten Thouſands, hath in theſe Nations for ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced your <hi>Sorcery, and Witchchraft,</hi> GLORY, GLO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY to God be given for ever, and for ever.</p>
            <p>And though you gather ſome <hi>heat</hi> from the <hi>Sun,</hi> that is newly ariſen, and from it receive ſome ſmall vigor, and like
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46207:5"/>
the <hi>Inſects,</hi> and the <hi>Reptilia</hi> of the Earth, who creep out of their holes, as they feel the Suns warmth, by which they are vivified and made ſtrong; yet know ſuch are not <hi>Parmanent,</hi> but the withdrawing of the Suns heat from them, ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to their holes, and ſome periſh; You may take this as a figure, for the Lord will cauſe the <hi>Sun</hi> to ſet, which hath quickened you; Then what will become of you? You will deſire ſtrongly to ſet with it alſo, but you ſhall not; <hi>For there is a cup prepared for you, being mixed with Plagues, Woes, Miſeries, Sorrows, Torments, and Eternal burnings,</hi> which you ſhall not paſſe; for you are found from the Lord God worthy, <hi>and a treble portion is to be given unto you;</hi> And ſo much for your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraleld fraud of your Soul Cure, which you impudently force the ſale of, upon people whether they will or nay, for which there is no example to be found amongſt all Chriſtian Miniſters, mentioned in Scriptures, neither amongſt ſober Tradſmen.</p>
            <p>We have ſomewhat to ſay, as to your entering into that Trade, or Function, which you call, <hi>Soul Cure;</hi> How came you thither? Prove your call, according to the Scripture, which you ſay is your Rule, and ſee with whom you run Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel; The Apoſtles were made Miniſters <hi>by the will of God, and not by the will of man;</hi> You are made Miniſters by the will of man, and not by the will of God; therefore you run not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel with them, who were Miniſters of Chriſt; And as to your Names, Orders, Geſtures, and Inventions, being no exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is found amongſt the Miniſters of Chriſt, they are all out of the Life and Truth, &amp; for Judgement; You aſſume to your ſelves names of <hi>Biſhops, Deacons,</hi> &amp;c. There is ſuch names mentioned in Scripture, but what is that to you? are you ever the more to be reverenced, becauſe of theſe names? (Nay,) except you were found in the Life of thoſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſpeaks of, You are never the better for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but much the worſe, except you be found in the Life of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Deacons</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Timothy</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I own the name <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and likewiſe <hi>Deacon,</hi> if they be as is there ſpoken of, <hi>viz. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreproveable, the husband of one Wife, Watching, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Modeſt, given to Hoſpitality, apt to Teach, not given to Wine, no Stricker, not given to filthy Lucre, but Gentle, no fighter, not Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteous;</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:46207:6"/>
Let me ask of you, are you ſo in all, or any of theſe things? Let that which is juſt of God in all your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, (Judge and Anſwer) if you be not, blame us not for denying of you; for we cannot own any to be a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Deacon,</hi> over us, except the name and Life go together; Theſe <hi>Biſhops and Deacons</hi> mentioned in Scripture, had not only the names, but they had the Life, from which the name proceeds; You have the name and want the Life, and ſo ſtands in a Lye; And when we come to compare you with thoſe that were in the Life of Righteouſneſſe, which is ſo in deed, and not in name, you are found utterly falſe, and to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed of all that fear the Lord.</p>
            <p>You have many old Names, whereby you diſtinguiſh your Orders, and Places, which the Scriptures of Truth neither knows nor owns; as <hi>Deans, Arch-deacons, Prebends, Countrey Deanes, Biſhops,</hi> called <hi>Suffragans,</hi> and ſeveral other; Whence had you or who gave you thoſe Names? Came not theſe from <hi>Rome?</hi> I am ſure the Miniſters of Chriſt left them not (upon record in Scripture;) ſo you cannot flie thither for ſhelter and refuge, neither can you cover your ſelves with their words; for <hi>the Light of Christ Jeſus which is the Life</hi> is ariſen, which doeth divide betwixt the Words and the Life, and hath ript up the falſe coverings, and ſo you ſtand quite naked, and <hi>wo is to him that is covered, and not with the Spirit of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You likewiſe rage if any call you <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and ſwell, and take that to be <hi>ignominious;</hi> but know, <hi>Prieſt</hi> was a good Name in its time, ſuch as were once ordained of God; But ſeeing you are angry at that, we grudge not the name of <hi>Miniſter</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you; for the prodigal Son was once a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> yea, and an Hireling too, as ſome Tranſlators renders it, read <hi>Luke</hi> 15.15. (as you are) Read what he Miniſtred, and to whom, but the Lord received him again after true Repentance, and then he left off ſerving of husks.</p>
            <p>And where is your example in Scripture, among the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt? For your running to the powers of Earth, and crying unto them for help, to ſetle you in your livings, and to get your falſe maintenance, called <hi>Tythes;</hi> With whom run you paralel? (Can you anſwer) and ſeeing Chriſts Miniſters did not ſo, you muſt needs be Antichriſts;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46207:6"/>
For there are but two ſorts of Miniſters, as I have ſaid; And where as you have ſaid and ſay, you are Chriſt Miniſters, and upon true ſearch it appeareth no ſuch thing, neither by your rule, nor example; Yet you run paralel with ſome mentioned in Scripture, (though not <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you rank your ſelves amongſt ſuch as were <hi>Chriſtian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> we will not go about to find out your paralel in the Old Teſtament; Though we might mention the orders of Prieſts there; for <hi>Aarons</hi> Order you have nothing to do with, for it was appointed of the Lord; Now there were other Orders of the Prieſts beſides <hi>Aarons,</hi> as <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, Prieſts of the <hi>Grove,</hi> and <hi>Jezebels Chaplins,</hi> which drew the ſame breſts as you do; But becauſe you ſay you are Chriſtian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, we ſhall ſay little more to them; But to thoſe which Chriſt and his Miniſters cried wo againſt, for they were in the ſame life you were in; The Scriptures of Truth make mention of ſuch <hi>as loved greetings in the Markets, and the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Roomes at Feaſts, and in the Synagogues, and Aſſemblies, and loved to be called of men Maſter;</hi> And do you not theſe things? Is it not ſo that you love greetings in the Markets, and the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt Rooms in your Synagogues, and Aſſemblies, and at <hi>Feaſts</hi> eſpecially; and you dearly love to be called of men <hi>Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will give you an inſtance of one of your Brethren of the (confuſed) <hi>Function,</hi> (though not of your <hi>Order</hi>) as he accounted himſelf; I met with him in the ſtreet, and he had ſome words with me, and I did call him by his Name, being known to me very wel; for he had often wrot his name as I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him; but the proud devil got up in him which would be called <hi>(Maſter)</hi> which was a name not for me to call him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept I had been his ſervant; and truly he denyed his name, and ſaid, <hi>his name was Maſter ſuch a one, before ſuch a Generation as I was got up;</hi> I asked him how he came by the name Maſter, for I told him I had aſſuredly ſeen him write his name other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; He told me <hi>he had ſerved for it at the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, and would be ſo called;</hi> And I told him that he that went by two names, was reckoned a cheat; Now you that loves to be called Maſter, do not call this man a fool in this, though truly he was ſo, except you your ſelves be clear of his folly, leaſt another
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46207:7"/>
may call you all fooles; for you as dearly love to be called ſo as he; <hi>I</hi> am ſure though <hi>I</hi> never ſaw any man of that Coat manifeſt his folly ſo much, but as to his art he had as much to ſay in it as moſt of you all whatſoever; we are comanded to <hi>call no man Maſter,</hi> for One is our Maſter, even One that you know not, for if you did, you would dread and fear him; and we do ordinarily call men by thoſe names as they call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their writings, if it be truth; and if you run not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel with the above mentioned in Scripture, being found in the ſame life and practice, let that which is Juſt of God in you Judge; for <hi>I</hi> have laid you to your direct line, Read <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. the chapter through.</p>
            <p>And the Scriptures of truth maketh mention of ſuch as were <hi>Blind guids,</hi> and that if <hi>the blind lead the blind they ſhall both fall into the Ditch;</hi> now perhaps you will ſay you run not paralel with the blind guides there ſpoken of, but I ſhall make it appear; know you wherefore they were called <hi>blind,</hi> they had eyes as well as you, and yet they were ſo, becauſe they could not ſee him who was come in the figure <hi>or fleſh,</hi> to fulfill and put an end to all that they did profeſs and practice in their worſhip and Religion, according to the Cerimonies of the Law; and becauſe they had been worſhipping in the types ſhaddows, and cerimonies, which held forth Chriſt till he came in the figure or fleſh, and when he was come and all theſe things in him fulfilled and ended, yet theſe that took upon them to be Teachers, Inſtructors, &amp; guides of the people could not ſee him, but continued ſtill in thoſe things which in him was fulfilled and ended; now were not theſe <hi>blind guides</hi> juſtly ſo called; and were not they that were led by them blind alſo, anſwer me; and did not the blind lead the blind, and was not the <hi>Pit</hi> the end of their journey; and did not theſe blind guides ſeduce people from the Doctrine and faith of Chriſt? which ſaid <hi>which of the Rulers have believed on him?</hi> was not this blind ſeducing? but perhaps you will ſay we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paralel with them, for we are <hi>Chriſtian Miniſters,</hi> &amp; we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he is come and hath fulfilled what is here mentioned; but I deny you are either Chriſts Miniſters or yet believers, for if you were his Miniſters, you would feed his flock, and not deſtroy them, &amp; not Lord it over them as you do, &amp; if you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46207:7"/>
in him you would do his works; but doing neither, you are neither Chriſtian Miniſters nor believers; The Scripture of truth maketh mention of ſeducers, <hi>Johns Epiſtle.</hi> 1, 2.26, 27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe things have I written unto you concerning them that ſeduce you, but the anointing of the Father which ye have received of him, abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anointing teacheth you of all things, and is truth and is no lye, and even as it hath taught ye, you ſhall abide in him;</hi> now you that are Miniſters of Confuſion, <hi>I</hi> aske you is this Scripture true or is it falſe? if it be true, as <hi>I</hi> think you dare not be ſo impudent as ſay the contrary, then your miniſtry is at an end, and utterly to be denyed of all that have received the <hi>anointing,</hi> for they have received that <hi>which is truth and no lye;</hi> you deny <hi>the Light of Chriſt within</hi> which is the <hi>anointing of the Father;</hi> therefore your preaching is a lye, ſeducing and Antichriſt, and utterly to be denyed; for as the blind guides ſaw not Chriſt when he came in the fleſh, to end and fulfill all their worſhips which ſtood in the Cerimonies of the Law, ſo you blind guides in this generation, ſee not Chriſt come in ſpirit, to lead, and guide, and inſtruct his people by the pure meaſure of his light manifeſted in this age &amp; generation; and all that hath received this, they have no need of your teaching; and therefore <hi>let all fleſh be ſilent before the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the blind guides did of old, ſo do you now; for they perſecuted Chriſt in the fleſh, and you perſecute him in ſpirit where ever he appears either in Male or Famale; and the blind guides would go on in their way, that was in their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple worſhip, and obſerving dayes, and offering Sacrifices, though <hi>their houſe were left unto them deſolate,</hi> and ſo do you go on in your way, though the witneſs of God riſe in you to condemne you for ſo doing; yet I put a vaſt difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Jews worſhip and yours, for it was true as it was once comanded of God, and it was a type of Chriſts coming in the fleſh; but yours was never comanded of God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a lye, but invented of them that were enemies to the appearance of Chriſt every way; and <hi>I</hi> deſire to know of you one thing, that is, what your worſhip is a type of, being you are enemies to the coming of Chriſt in ſpirit, and cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46207:8"/>
him where ever he appears, and what it is that muſt ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill it; but this is a Doctrine you cannot endure to hear of, it is as the pangs of Death to you; what to ſpeak of having your Doctrine to come to an end? how will thoſe ſayings be fulfilled <hi>then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, allwaies learning &amp; never able to come to the knowledge of the truth?</hi> For this will pleaſe you better, that you may be ever teaching, though betwixt the <hi>Womb</hi> and the <hi>Tomb,</hi> people be never the better, but much the worſe, and them that hangs on your Doctrine to the end, they are undone for ever.</p>
            <p>Now Read your ſelves paralel with the blind guids.</p>
            <p>And as to all your trinketts and inventions not worth nameing, and even as it were numberleſs, hath God choſen or required this at your hands, to be his worſhip, (if he have) then without doubt he hath choſen you to be Miniſters, of it; but I am ſure he hath neither choſen this for his worſhip, neither you for his Miniſters, for this is the worſhip God hath choſen, <hi>even ſpirit</hi> and not art and invention; and ſo likewiſe his Miniſters that he hath choſen, are poor, weak, diſpiſed Ones, which is to the confounding of you and your Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</p>
            <p>The Scripture maketh mention of one <hi>Simon</hi> which uſed ſorcery and witch-crafts, read <hi>Acts</hi> 8, 9. In ſome things you paralel him, for he uſed ſorcery and bewitched people, But he believed and continued a ſeaſon, and he profferd money for the gift of the <hi>Holy ſpirit,</hi> that he might do as the Apoſtles did, but he was curſed with his money, becauſe he would purchas the gift of God with it, which is not to be done; now had it been poſſible that the gift of God could have been bought with money, however <hi>Simon</hi> (had bought the truth) and it is no doubt but he would have made ſale of it again, he would have ſold the truth though his end was curſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was for gain; now you are found not to be of <hi>Simons</hi> mind, for you are far from buying the truth, for you buy lyes &amp; ſell them again, and hath them, and ſells them again many times over; now <hi>Simons</hi> Condition was more innocent and harmleſs then yours, for there was a place of repentance found for him, and an exhortation unto it, <hi>verſe</hi> 22. Truly I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay ſo of you, <hi>I</hi> deſire I could.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:46207:8"/>The Scripture maketh mention of one <hi>Elymas</hi> a ſorcerer, being by interpretation ſo called <hi>Acts</hi> 13.8. And with him you run paralel; for the Deputy having received the faith of Jeſus, he with ſtood the Apoſtles and ſought to turn him away from it, but he was ſtruck with blindneſs which was his reward; and you do as your Brother did, for if any, eſpecially Rulers or men in Authority, do come to own the truth as it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in them by the Light of Jeſus, Oh what ſtirring and ſtriving, by reviling and reproching, by ſhifts and lyes, do you make to ſmother and ſtifle it; and what calumnies, aſperſions, and ſlanders do you caſt upon the Miniſters there of, calling of them Seducers, Deceivers, Heathens, and Jeſuites, with many other filthy names, to turn the minds of any who have received it, from it again; and not ſo contented, but calls <hi>the Light within</hi> damnable Hereſie, damnable Blaſphemy, a Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of Devils, Popery, and ſo forth; now is not this <hi>Elymas</hi> like (or worſe) for it may be he might not caſt ſo many ſlanders upon the Apoſtles and the faith, as you do upon them now who Miniſter in the faith; but <hi>Elymas</hi> withſtood the Apoſtles to turn the Deputie from the faith, &amp; who knoweth but <hi>Elymas</hi> might have a great part of his gain from that Deputie; it is very probable that before he received the faith of Jeſus at the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles preaching, he might believe <hi>Elymas</hi> his ſorcery, and ſo truly <hi>Elymas</hi> might receive much pay for it of him, for Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and deviners, ſuch as <hi>Elymas</hi> and you are, gives not your comodities <hi>(Gratis)</hi> But are payd for them to purpoſe, as Thouſands of my Friends in <hi>England</hi> and other parts can witneſs, though they receive none of your ſorcery, yet you take by violence their goods and money from them, like Theeves, and pretends a Law for it; Truely in this you out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip all your Brother-hood mentioned in Scriptures both in old and new Teſtament, as ever <hi>I</hi> read of; <hi>I</hi> have read of ſome who took the wages of unrighteouſneſs, But <hi>I</hi> know not whether (by force or nay) as you do; I never read of any that took treeble damage as you do, and yet wo was pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch who took ſuch wages, and if wo were their portion what will be yours who exceeds them in all their wickedneſs and abominations? ſurely, ſurely Hell hath enlarged her lips wide for you, and it was high time for <hi>Elymas</hi> to withſtand the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46207:9"/>
Apoſtles and the Faith, being the Deputy had received it, and ſtand up for his God, which had received ſuch a knock, as could not be recovered, but by turning the Deputy who had received the Faith from it again; What a condition was <hi>Elimas</hi> in, his ſocery would not ſerve, for the Truth was received, therefore his God muſt famiſh; And truly ſo it is with you, for if any comes to receive the Truth, then comes your ſorcery and deceit to be made manifeſt; and though formerly it hath been account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good ware, whilſt no better was known; But now that is a riſen in people in this Nation, which hath laid open all your deceits, and falſe cheats, and rips up all your deceitful coverings, and hath turned your inſide outward; I ſpeak not this only of you who are now the Merchants of the time, but I ſpeak of all, and of all orders whatſoever, called or known by, out of the Life of Truth, which the Lord God hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by his Light, You are all utterly to be denied in the ſight of God for ever; and as to moſt of your brethren which you have ſupplanted, and turned out of their Markets and Shops, a while ſince they pleaded more right to them then you, now you plead more right to them then they, and ſo one brother ſupplanting another; You need not deal ſo cruelly with them as many ſay you do, they are your brothers, for you have all one Mother, and hath ſucked all one breaſt, and ſo you are all of one nature, and they are as ready in the work of perſecution, and as active as you can be; Therefore accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the equity of that, they might joyn with you in your trading, as ſome already hath done, for they are very diligent and hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and if they may not be allowed to be ſhop-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, let them be, ſhop-ſweepers, for rather then ſit our, they will do any thing; I know they are ſtiffe and proud, but they muſt acknowledge you to be their Eldeſt brother, and your Father doth ſo compute you; But know this aſſuredly, you are brethren in iniquitie, and your whole lives, practices and profeſſions, being condemned by the Spirit of God, and the Apoſtles, and Scriptures, ſtands in a lie, and ſo to be denied of all that fear the Lord; You are even diſcovered and known to be as you are, <hi>viz.</hi> Antichriſts, Deceivers, Socerers, and ravening Wolves, and you rage, and your fury is kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46207:9"/>
and caſts out whole floods of ſlanders, and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, after the Truth, becauſe your God which is your belly is in danger to be ſtarved and famiſhed, for you know not, neither will you know, any way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring your ſacrifices for your God, but that curſed way, that is, by extracting of them from the drops of ſweat that runs from other mens faces; for you abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and abhor labour, and the Scriptures which ſaith, <hi>In the ſweat of thy face thou ſhalt eat thy bread, and he that will not work ſhall not eat,</hi> you ſeldom or never make uſe of, and ſo you may offer fat Sacrifices unto your God (which is your belly) obtaining them at thoſe rates; but know aſſuredly as you have taken and wrung the drops of ſweat from the faces of ſuch as have had no dealings with you, (eſpecially) the Lord God hath put them with their Tears alſo up into a bottle, which he keeps for a perpetual memorial of their Innocent ſufferings, &amp; your cruelty, and tyranny, &amp; injuſtice; therefore <hi>Flames, Flames, Flames of fire is prepared by the Lord to conſume you as dry ſtubble;</hi> In the Light of the eternal God I have beheld you and all your actions, and take them all together, and Rake the pit of confuſion, and bind up your ſtuff in a bundle, and indeed there is no paralel nor never was, that ever I could read of, or hear amongſt any Miniſters, Chriſtian, or Antichriſtian, or amongſt ſober Trades-men, or Artiſts whatſoever, but you out-ſtrip all of them in your way of wickedneſs; if I ſhould paralel you with <hi>Salvage Beaſts,</hi> I could not truely do it, I think be they never ſo fierce, for they ſtand in kind, Beaſts of prey, anſwereth the end of their Creation, and ſo doth all other Creatures of the <hi>Salvage kind;</hi> but men of prey ſuch as you are, is quit out of kind, and not to be paraleld by any thing that draweth breath; Oh what ſhall I ſay of you, <hi>I have ſeen you, I have ſeen you, in the eternal, and you are the pooreſt, Creatures that hath Communion with the Common ayre;</hi> every Creature anſwereth the end of his Creation but man, yet
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46207:10"/>
notwithſtanding as man is in the ſimplicity found, there is a remedy for him; but for you the worſt of men, Oh full of all ſubtilty, Children generated of the ſeed of deceit, brought forth out of the womb of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp; nouriſhed up at the breaſts of witch-craft, &amp; rocked in the cradle of Idleneſs, <hi>wo is me for you, for the day which I ſee is comming upon you from the Lord, and all them that you have made drunk, by putting your bottle of Poyſon to their noſes, who have drunk deep, and ſo are become one in nature with you; it had been better you had never been born, It had been better for you, that you had been ſtrangled in your Mothers Wombs, and ſtill births had been preſented to them, then Living Children into their Armes;</hi> Oh what ſhall I ſay concerning you, <hi>Gods everlaſting decree is Sealed againſt you, burnings, burnings, burnings, with unquenchable fire is your portion from the Lord God of Heaven and Earth,</hi> whoſe pure ſpirit you have long grieved; Oh how have you been warned, admoniſhed, exhorted, and reproved, and in true love to your ſouls, by the Servants of the Lord, of the day which is even coming upon you, and you have not taken warning of them, but for their love you have rewarded them with whippings, ſtocks, and impriſonments, and ſpoyl of goods, and ſome loſs of life, whoſe blood is treaſured up againſt the day of your account; dreadfull will it be to you for there is no covering found for you, neither refuge to fly unto, it is the hand of the Lord that hath ſearched you out, and there is no reſiſting of it; Oh it is the hand of the Lord that is ſtrong and mighty, And Oh that men that are brought forth in time, ſtands in time, and ends in time, ſhould contend with eternity; did ever the leſſer comprehend the greater, ſpeak and anſwer, if not, then how dare you preſume to frame and invent a worſhip to the eternal God, and under the name of <hi>Goſpel-worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Miniſtry;</hi> is he worſhipped in Temples made with hands, or <hi>Stone-houſes,</hi> falſely by you <hi>called Churches,</hi> or think you your <hi>Altars</hi> and turned <hi>Pillars</hi> called <hi>Railes,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:46207:10"/>
your <hi>Organs,</hi> your <hi>Singing-Men,</hi> and <hi>Boyes,</hi> with <hi>Surplices, Tippits, Scarffs, Long Garments, and Girdles,</hi> with your invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>prayer</hi> called <hi>Common,</hi> with your preaching, and the beſt of your ſacrifices, enters into the ears of the eternal God; (nay) you are highly miſtaken, <hi>A pure God</hi> muſt have pure praiſe, God praiſes God; his praiſe and worſhip for ever and ever, is from <hi>thee</hi> unto <hi>thee;</hi> now if you cannot read this, let your mouths for ever be ſtopped; and ceaſe your Invented Inſtruments for worſhip, for an evil Savour doth your ſacrifices ſend forth, even a loathing to the Lord God of Heaven and Earth; but the God which you Imagine, let him be worſhipped according to your Imaginations and inventions; and think not to mock the <hi>Eternal God</hi> by your Devices; I tell you again, as <hi>I</hi> have ſaid, it is <hi>Spirit</hi> and not <hi>Art,</hi> except you will dare to preſume to make the Lord God any thing elſe but a <hi>Spirit,</hi> if you do, you are Blaſphemers in the higheſt degree: <hi>Oh I have ſeen eternity, I have ſeen eternity,</hi> and a dreadfull day is very near at hand to be revealed, <hi>Oh the overflowing ſcourge, Oh the Beſome of deſtruction, Oh the plague and vengeance that is to be powred upon the wicked in this Nation, both Prieſt and People; howl, howl, Hireling Prieſts of all Orders, for the Wine-Preſs of the wrath of God Almighty is even near to be trod, into which you are to be caſt, for the Lord God hath ſpoken it, and he will not repent;</hi> a trebble por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a trebble portion of the Plagues of God Almighty, are you to have above all others; Juſt, Holy, and True, Art thou God eternal that hath thus judged, and thy judgements are holy, juſt, and true, <hi>Praiſes, Praiſes</hi> from the immortal pure ſeed, in all thine be given unto thee for ever and for ever.</p>
            <p>What more ſhall I ſay of you, Oh you miſerable &amp; moſt wretched! you have been the ring-leaders to blood-ſhed, you have been the ring-leaders to perſecution, your hands are full of it; You have been the men that hath ſpurred on the Magiſtrate, to lay violent and cruel hands on the Innocent, when many times they would not have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46207:11"/>
done it, and you have given them no reſt, till they have fulfilled and ſatisfied your bloody minds; and very few of you, but have <hi>changed</hi> with every <hi>change,</hi> you have ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every Power, &amp; have been true to none; Oh moſt deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful! you have in all theſe overtures and changes, which hath been wrought in theſe Nations, of late years, Kept your heads above the water, and have floated along with the ſtreams when many who have gone hand in hand with you, hath ſunk in every change, and eſpecially this late; Oh! what ſhall I ſay, my bowels, my bowels, I bear a burden for you, which I cannot utter; Oh! your deceitful flatterie; Oh! how have you blaſphemed God, and hath aſcribed to man, <hi>whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils,</hi> that which belongeth not unto him, eſpecially if he ſtands in his unregenerated eſtate; Had, and have you not curſed ends in this? Anſwer, Are, or were they ſo as you beſpeak, and do beſpeak them to be? One thing I aſſuredly know, that the Powers ſince, and the Powers preſent, never ſaid ſo of themſelves, whatever they thought and think, as you ſaid, and ſay; And all for the ſake of your God, which is your Belly; Did not many of you to the Powers gone, aſcribe names, to them that they never knew nor witneſſed the Life in the leaſt, of whom you ſpake? And do you not now aſcribe to the <hi>chief Power,</hi> that which I am ſure he calls not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? As <hi>the expreſſe Image of the Heavenly Father;</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe your <hi>Surry</hi> addreſſe to him, ſigned by ſo many Doctors of D. St. of. D.<note place="margin">See it in the publick Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth the 16. of the 6. Month D. D. St D. L. L. D.</note> as you call your ſelves; Now was ever any called <hi>the expreſſe Image of the Heavenly Father,</hi> but Chriſt Jeſus? And think you the <hi>chief Magiſtrate</hi> of theſe Nations, doth not ſee your ends, and your flatteries in this, and many other things? I am perſwaded, when ever his mind comes truly to be turned, to that which is juſt of God <hi>in him,</hi> He will ſee you to be even ſo as I have ſaid, the greateſt <hi>Sycophants,</hi> and Flaterers, that lives in theſe Nations; Wo, wo, wo, unto you, for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46207:11"/>
you are of that Generation, upon whom all the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous blood, from <hi>Abel,</hi> even to this day, have been charged; <hi>Oh! dreadful God, muſt it be ſo that thy decree which thou haſt ſealed, muſt come to paſſe, and be fulfilled in this Generation; And muſt theſe fill up the cup of their great Grand-fathers,</hi> Bonner and Gardener, &amp;c. <hi>By powring out the blood of thy dear purchaſed Lambs in this Generation;</hi> (If ſo) <hi>Thy will Infinite God be done, and Glorifie thy ſelf in what thou haſt decreed, Eternal God, for thou art right worthy to be Feared, Praiſed, Honoured, and Glorified, of all thy Children and dear Lambs, for ever and for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But certainly know this, it muſt be your bloody Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which you will offer, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Lambs of Jeſus,</hi> That will ſink you into the Pit of Eternal deſtruction; for your next fall will be as the fall <hi>of a Milſtone into the Sea,</hi> (Read that) GOD ETERNAL <hi>hath ſpoken it, and</hi> I <hi>faithfully believe it, and moſt of you are the men muſt perform it, and ſhall ſee it, and feel it, before you go away from hence, and be no more ſeen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for me, an object of the living mercy of the Eternal God, who as <hi>a brand pluckt out of the fire,</hi> and as a Fowl that narrowly eſcapes <hi>the Fowlers net,</hi> ſo I, even I, am brought out of your confuſion and ſorcery, <hi>Praiſes, praiſes,</hi> be given to the Imortal God, from thy, pure ſeed in me, and all, for ever, and for ever; And by thy pure Power am I made to ſtand a witneſſe, againſt all falſe teachers, both in <hi>England,</hi> and the reſt of the Nations whatſoever, in my meaſure, and by whatſoever names they are called and diſtinguiſhed, being all out of the Life and Truth; And rage not againſt me becauſe of my teſtimony here written; for I have ſaid you to your line, &amp; ſtretched it over you, and if you fall ſhort, let that riſe in you, that will ſhew you the cauſe; And I have compared you with your example mentioned in Scripture, <hi>viz. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46207:12"/>
Miniſters,</hi> And anſwering not them, you have reaſon to be ſilent, and ſtop your mouths, and ſit down con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, to be ranked and paralel'd with them that lived the ſame life, that you are found in; For to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare you with ſuch, is truth, and no ſlander; and ſo I finiſh this my Teſtimony concerning you.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errours.</head>
            <p>Page 4. line 7. for know read come, Page 7. l. 16. for Miniſters read Miniſters of Chriſt, l. 22. for as read up.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46207:12"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
